what do I do if my ftin level is low and
we see that a lot right normal ftin like
we were saying for men is from 30 to 400
for most some are 15 to 360 but it's a
very wide range and as I told you right
now optimal we'd like ftin to be about
40 to 100 in the mid 50s or so what
happens if your Fatin goes below this
low fertin is as bad if not worse than
high fertin and high iron because as we
said we need iron for life so sometimes
you'll see patients coming they have a
normal hemoglobin but their ftin is low
in one of your questions this this
reader um said his ftin was down to two
that's very low so you can have a low
ftin and your hemoglobin did not change
yet because that's the first thing that
we see your ftin goes down and ftin is
pretty sensitive for iron stores when
it's low when fertin is high there's
different reasons but when it's low it
usually will reflect a low iron status
so when I see a patient with low fertin
the first thing we got to ask why do you
have low fiin and there's only a few
things that can cause low fertin you're
losing blood somehow someway or you not
absorbing enough iron so when I see a
low ftin I ask why is this happening is
the patient donating blood and if you
donate blood within the first 6 to eight
weeks if you check your Labs your iron
indices are going to going to be on the
lower side because your body did not
recycle remake all the iron that it
needs after donating blood if you over
donating so you donate too much yeah you
can have a negative balance and that's
what we tend to see a lot with guys on
testosterone because they hear donate
blood if you take testosterone because
testosterone can induce secondary Earth
poesis so you see an increase in
hemoglobin and hematocrite but you can't
donate blood blindly and following the
hemoglobin is not good enough you need
to follow the it so the the situation I
found a lot of my patients and that's
why I started taking checking iron is
they donate too much and they drop their
fertin and when you drop your fertin you
have a lot of the same symptoms you
could get with high iron so low iron
levels causes a lot of anxiety
depression even it's been associated
with ADHD you feel tired low energy a
shorter breath you can't exert yourself
um you have reflexes so sometimes your
your arm moves you start wanting to eat
um non food items people want to eat ice
they want to eat chalk it's bad for your
heart it's bad for your brain so low
iron is bad but having a low fertin you
need to know why so number one would be
are you donating blood too much if
you're not donating we need to look for
another the number two would be that
you're losing blood in the GI system
chronic gastritis if you're taking
medication like anti-inflammatory
medication like abueno Advil low do
asterin causes micro beding and if
you're 40 or more and any age and you
see that you have a low iron and if you
can't find a reason for it you need a GI
workup I've had many patients who came
to me with low iron when they went and
did a colonoscopy endoscopy either they
find chronic gastritis or more commonly
they'll find polyps in their colon and
popse is start bleeding micros
microscopically and eventually confirm
into colon cancer so if somebody has low
fertin you need to know why it's not
just let me take iron so my first
question is let's find out why and
there's a differential diagnosis if it
is bleeding that you're bleeding if
there's chronic gastritis they can laser
it if you have a pop they take it out if
you are donating blood too much you stop
donating if another reason that I saw
it's poor absorption of iron so
something like and I've diagnosed how
many three people with this celiac
disease when you have celiac disease you
have blunting of of the cells of the the
small intestine and more difficult to
absorb different different elements
different minerals ion is one of them so
I've found some patients who are
deficiency when who went down the list
their cause of iron deficiency was
celiac disease so for people to kind of
think again don't just say I have low F
let me take iron first question we need
to answer why do you have low fertin do
we need more testing now once we've
established the cause you try
to you know stop the cause if you're
donating blood too much stop donating
until your fertin goes up if you have
bleeding somewhere deal with it but if
at the the end of the day we found okay
you were over donating let's say you
stopped donating how do you increase
your fertin level is always the big
question and there's different ways of
doing this for sure if you have a low
fertin you want to go on iron
replacement shortterm until you get your
ftin like this guy who had two I want
him in the 30 50 60 range right so you
take different ways you can in increase
your dietary intake of iron eating more
iron rich foods like like and you want
to eat mostly foods that have he iron
because he versus non-he Iron has better
absorption and that's what you'll find
in animal products like red meat
shellfish poultry pork uh non heem iron
you will get that from um vegetables
like beans spinach it has a lower
absorption so you want to really do a
lot of H iron combine that with vitamin
C so if you want to absorb your your
your iron you make sure that your meat
you put some lemon juice on it so that
helps with your absorption and if you
need now supplements because a lot of
times that may not be enough to do it
just by diet which iron supplements
should you take so I'm not going to give
like a Brin per se but for example ion
sulfate feo4 is what we usually
recommend more the absorption is not
great I like more um Iron he ion
supplements meaning that they comes from
an animal Source they have much better
absorption so if you're going to take an
ion form it has to be a he ion and
here's something something that is very
important um you cannot take iron
tablets daily every day it's better to
skip it because I'm going to speak about
a A protein that we talked about the
last time and we're going to spend a lot
of time talking about this hsid so
Heiden it is the main regulator of of
iron physiology Heiden was only
discovered in 2001 only 23 years ago so
I found out about heidin last year most
people haven't heard about that molecule
and the physiology because it's pretty
new and it is it's there's no
commercially available test to check
your Iden level but it makes sense the
physiology so now let me go a little bit
about the physiology of iron the way we
get iron into our body is we get it from
two sources either from dietary intake
what we eat um and that's usually about
two to 5% of the iron that's in our
blood we get from our diet pretty small
most of the rest of the comes from the
recycling endothelial
system that gets into the spleen so when
our old red cells die they go to the
spleen they get destroyed and by the
mcroof fages and the macras keep that
iron so Heiden also regulates the
recycling of iron that accounts for 90
to 98% of the iron in our blood meaning
that when the red cells get destroyed
they keep the iron depending on Heiden
it will decide whether they keep the
iron in the split or release it into the
blood to go for new red cells so heidin
is in the middle of this it's secreted
by the liver and in the case of normal
or high ion stores you have a high level
of Iden and what Heiden does it goes and
blocks the absorption of ion in the
intestine and it also blocks the release
of ion from the macres so just picture
that is the way we get iron into US you
have two um lines
coming in one from the intestine one
from the macrofagos from the spleen
heidin blocks both of those so you have
high ion stores those two lines are
blocked your iron Stores stay the same
although you're eating ion your body is
not absorbing it if you have low ion
stores your Heiden levels goes down
remove the block from those lines now
you absorb iron and you put iron from
the spleen into the blood test so Heiden
is the roller of those lines it either
turns it off or it turns it in when you
take ion supplements the body is very
has very tight mechanisms to control
iron because it knows the human body is
smart it knows that we need iron but too
much is bad so get just enough when you
take iron tablets it raises your Heiden
and it makes sense right the body you
take iron usually we don't take that
much so iron you can take from 15
milligram
up to 200 migr tablet so when you get a
those like the body is like oh we have
enough iron block the channels and you
block the Heiden level stays elevated
for 12 to 24 hours so I used to
recommend from my conventional training
iron sulfate twice a day the one you
take in the afternoon you're barely
absorbing anything of it because you are
high heidin at the moment the the the
the lines are blocked so if you're going
to take iron it's recommend to skip a
day take it every 48 hours every 72
hours because by the time you take your
next dose 48 or 72 hours later your hi
siding level went down the the lines are
open so your body will absorb more of it
great another thing that's really
important and a lot of my patients I
don't even put them it's not too low you
don't even put them on iron supplements
I like desiccated uh liver um
supplements so liver is the most
important um reservoir of iron in the
body that's why if you look at every um
apex predator when they make a kill they
go straight for the liver they know
that's where they get the iron the
copper the magnesium the vitamin A all
of those good supplements minerals and
vitamins that you need so taking
desiccated liver um ex extract of liver
from a good source uh you want to be
sure that those are grass-fed you know
no no no pesticides no growth hormone um
Bine growth hormone you want the
cleanest Source possible uh because in a
lot of cases you get some iron but you
get what's most important in iron
physiolog is copper copper as a mineral
completely controls iron balance so a
lot of times you can have people who
have either low iron or another form of
of anemia called the anemia of chronic
disease where your iron is not low it's
just unavailable to you when you have
this you take just copper the right
amount of copper and you can liberate
your own sources of iron so very
important so low iron I think we've
established although we're going to talk
after that about iron overload but low
iron low fertin is as dangerous if not
more dangerous actually iron deficiency
anemia is one of the most common
nutritional deficiencies in the world it
affects mostly women of who have their
period women after pregnancy and young
kids young children who may not have the
right the the right um nutritional
supplements nutritional intake of iron
so it is really
important